Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is דף ז *daf
zayin*, בבא מציעא *Bava Metzia* ז *zayin*. We pick up three lines
from the top. אמר ליה amar leh, רב אחאי מדפתי *Amar leh
Rav Achai mi-Difti* and our learning should be in memory of my
nephew, Maoz Morel, מעוז בן איתן וורדה דבורה *Maoz ben Eitan u-Varda
Devora*, זכר צדיק לברכה *Zecher tzadik livracha*, who fell defending עם ישראל
*Am Yisrael* and מדינת ישראל *Medinat Yisrael*.
Okay, yesterday we wrapped up an important discussion about the principle of
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה *Hamotzi mechavero alav harayah*, whether that means that,
you know, if there's a doubt, we say the person who's trying
to take it out of the other person's hands, he has the
burden of proof. Does that mean that we really don't know whose
it is and we leave it as a big question mark and
we just say we're throwing up our hands as a בית דין
*beit din* and we're not going to do anything? If that's the
case, then if the second person were to take it out of
the hands of the first, we would also leave it in the
hands of the second. And it could go ping-ponging back and forth.
That's a principle of תקפו כהן אין מוציאין מידו *takfo kohen ein
motzi'in miyado*. Or do we say no, we are actually ruling, at
least tentatively, until we have to, might revise it if other evidence
presents itself, but we're actually ruling that it does belong in the
hands of the, that it's owned by the person who is currently
in possession of it, and if the other guy grabs it, he
would not be able to keep it. תקפו כהן אין מוציאין מידו
*takfo kohen ein motzi'in miyado*, excuse me, מוציאין מידו *motzi'in miyado*. And
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* concluded that we say the second, that because
of these cases in the that we were dealing with about ספק
בכור *sefek bechor* and so on, it would only have made sense
and you normally, you know, it has to be עשירי ודאי *asiri
vadai*, not עשירי ספק *asiri safek*, you have to be certain that
it's מעשר *ma'aser*, that it only makes sense if we're actually ruling
as a matter of דיני ממונות *dinei mamanus* that it belongs to
the person whose hands it's in, and if the other guy would
take it, he would have to give it back. Of course, it
should be mentioned that from an איסור *issur* perspective that could be
different and that would be why it would still have קדושת בכור
*kedushas bechor*. Okay, so now we are going to just wrap up
this discussion about what was this case of ספקות *sfekos* that you
would take מעשר בהמה *ma'aser behemah* on. אמר ליה רב אחאי מדפתי
לרבינא מאי ספקות *Amar leh Rav Achai mi-Difti le-Ravina Mai sfekos*? What's
the case when it says that if you have a ספק *safek*
in the
בכור *bechor* that was born to you, you would bring it in
with your other baby animals and you would take מעשר בהמה *ma'aser
behemah* from it? What's the scenario? אילימא ספק בכורות *Ileyma safek bechoros*,
if there's, you know, it's a question of a firstborn sheep or
not, קדוש kadosh, אמר רחמנא ולא שכבר קדוש kadosh. *kadosh amar rachmana
velo she-kevar kadosh*. The tenth will be holy and not something that's
already holy. So how can you have it among your other sheep?
This might be already a קדושת בכור *kedushas bechor* and then obviously
taking מעשר *ma'aser* from it would not make any sense. אלא ספק
פדיון פטר חמור *Ella safek pidyon peter chamor*. What we're talking about
is that it was a ספק *safek* of you had a donkey
that gave birth and you didn't know if it was the first
animal or not, if it was the בכור *bechor*, so you redeemed
it with a sheep, and in that case the sheep is, what
do you call, the sheep is does not have קדושת בכור *kedushas
bechor*, even if it was, even if the donkey was
a definite פטר חמור *peter chamor*, it would not have any קדושה
kedusha *kedusha*. It would just be the money of a כהן *kohen*.
But since you don't know whether it was or not, so you're
presumed to be the owner and you can take מעשר בהמה *ma'aser
behemah* though because either way it doesn't have any קדושה kedusha *kedusha*,
even if it should be going to the כהן *kohen*, it is
only his monetarily, not in terms of any קדושה kedusha *kedusha*. Okay,
so אלא ספק פדיון פטר חמור כדרב נחמן *Ella safek pidyon peter
chamor kid-Rav Nachman*, like רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* teaches, דאמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה ישראל שיש לו עשרה ספק פטרי חמור בתוך
ביתו *De-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha Yisrael she-yesh lo asarah
sfek pitrei chamor betoch beito*. If a ישראל *Yisrael*, a non כהן
*kohen*, has ten cases of animals that were redeemed by a פטר
חמור *peter chamor* in his house, first we have the ten baby
donkeys and each one of them might be a בכור *bechor* from
ten different mothers, and they all might be, none of them might
be, or whatever. What do you do? מפריש עליהן עשרה שהיין *Mafrish
aleihen asarah se'in*, you separate ten sheep and you redeem each sheep
on a donkey, all out of ספק *safek*. And now of these
ten sheep, it's all either they all belong to a כהן *kohen*,
they all belong to you, some belong to a כהן *kohen*, some
belong to you, you don't know. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה *Hamotzi mechavero
alav harayah*, so you are the presumed owner. There's no קדושה *kedusha*,
because even if they belong to a כהן *kohen*, there's no קדושה
*kedusha*, and therefore ומעשרן והן שלו *u-masran ve-hen shelo*. And therefore you
take מעשר *ma'aser* and they're all yours. The nine are
yours and the tenth is yours because מעשר בהמה *ma'aser behemah* belongs
to the owner. Okay, so that's just the case of how you
would do it, but as we said yesterday, that only makes works
if you say that תקפו כהן אין מוציאין מידו *takfo kohen ein
motzi'in miyado*, that we're ruling that you are the presumed owner. And
that's how you can use it for מעשר *ma'aser* even when they
don't have קדושה *kedusha*. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: מאי הוה לה דאמשותא *Mai hava la ded-amshuta*? If you remember,
this whole case got we got to it because we asked a
question of grabbing a טלית tallis, *tallis* and the person was silent
and then he started yelling, and is that considered like he is
admitting that it's your that it was initially silent? And the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* said what would happen if he were to sanctify, if
he were to... fight with that be like grabbing it out of
his hands? We interpret the silence the same way. And then the
גמרא Gemara brought a case about this bathhouse which somebody did exactly
that and the rabbis didn't bathe in it, so that seems to
show that the act of sanctifying it is like a type of
a grabbing it and would make you sort of the owner, and
the guy's silence would be a concession that you were the owner.
But that was the initial part of the conversation. Let's see how
it ended up. מאי הוה עלה דמסותא? Mai hava ala demasuta? What
was the upshot of the bathhouse case? תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear, דאמר רב חייא בר אבין, Deamar Rav Chiya bar Avin,
הוי עובדא בי רב חסדא. Hava uvda bei Rav Chisda. There was
this case occurred in the house of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. If
you remember originally it was supposed to be brought to רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, רב חסדא בר רב הונא, Rav Chisda bar Rav Huna,
and רב חסדא Rav Chisda forwarded this question onto רב הונא. Rav
Huna. ופשטה, Upashta, and he concluded
it מהא דאמר רב נחמן, Meha deamar Rav Nachman, כל ממון שאינו
יכול להוציאו בדיינין הקדישו אינו קדוש. Kol mamon sheino yakhol lehotzio bedayanin
hekdesho eino kadosh. Any money that you cannot extract with judges, so
your sanctifying does not make it holy. So since there was obviously
the whole case of the bathhouse was nobody could prove whose it
was, so since you couldn't prove that it was yours, your act
you didn't have enough control over it that your act of sanctifying
it did not make it קדוש, did not make it holy. And
as far as the earlier discussion, it sounds like we're just assuming
that the other person's silence does not become like an admission that
it's yours and therefore it's seen to be yours and therefore your
קדושה made it קדוש. No, since you walked into that case and
you couldn't prove it's yours, your act is a meaningless act, and
since it's a meaningless act, the silence means nothing, because why should
he respond? And therefore it did not have קדושה as opposed to
how the rabbis had been acting regarding it, that they were staying
away from it. So now the גמרא Gemara just has a question.
כל ממון שאינו יכול להוציאו בדיינין הקדישו קדוש? Kol mamon sheino yakhol
lehotzio bedayanin hekdesho kadosh? Are you telling me that if it's something
that you can prove it's yours, then your sanctifying works even when
it's in the hands of somebody else, אע"ג דלא אפקיה, Af al
gav delo afkei,
even before you've taken it out of the hands of the other
person? והאמר רב יוחנן, Vehaamar Rav Yochanan, גזל ולא נתייאשו הבעלים, Gazel
velo nityasu habaalim,
if somebody steals something and the owners have not given up hope,
שניהם אינם יכולים להקדישו, Sheneihem einam yakholim lehakdisho,
neither party can sanctify it. זה לפי שאינו שלו, Ze lefi sheino
shelo, the גזלן gazlan can't because it's not his, וזה לפי שאינו
ברשותו, Veze lefi sheino birshuto, and the owner can't because he right
now is not under physical control of it, even though eventually he'll
get it back because he could prove it's his. So why do
you make it sound that once you can prove it, that already
it's enough under your control to sanctify it? רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
says explicitly not that way, it needs to be physically under your
control. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha bemai askinan,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מי סברת במסותא מטלטלין עסקינן?
Mi savrat demasuta metalatlin askinan?
What makes you think we're talking about a type of portable bathhouse?
What's a portable bathhouse? רש"י Rashi says it's a barrel, a barrel
you would fill with water. Okay, so if that were the case,
then you're right, then it's in physical possession of the other person.
Even if you can prove that it's yours, since it's away from
you and the other person has it under their control and it's
in their physical possession, your sanctifying would be meaningless even if you
could prove it's yours. That would be you would be right if
we were talking about a portable bathhouse. No, במסותא מקרקעי עסקינן. Bemasuta
mekarkei askinan. We're talking about a bathhouse that's in the ground, that's
actually a structure. And in that case, כיון דיכול להוציאו בדיינין ברשותיה
קיימא. Keivan deyakhul lehotzio bedayanin birshuteih kaima. Since you can't actually physically
take land away, you can sit on somebody's land. Once you can
prove it's yours, it's always considered to be under your control. We
never have the idea of אינו ברשותו eino birshuto by land just
because somebody is sitting on your land. If you can prove it's
yours, then it's already seen to be under your control. Okay, so
that would be since it's land, once you can prove it's yours
you can sanctify it, but here since he couldn't prove it's yours,
the sanctifying was a meaningless act and therefore the other person's silence
was
likewise don't import any meaning to that and therefore the קדושה does
not work. Okay. תני רב תחליפא בר מערבא קמיה דרבי אבהו. Tani
Rav Tachlifa bar Maarava kamey deRabbi Abbahu. רב תחליפא בר מערבא Rav
Tachlifa bar Maarava taught in front of רבי אבהו: Rabbi Abbahu: שנים
אדוקים בטלית, זה נוטל עד מקום שידו מגעת וזה נוטל עד מקום
שידו מגעת, והשאר חולקים בשווה. Shenayim adukim betallit, ze notel ad makom
sheyado magaat veze notel ad makom sheyado magaat, vehashar cholkim beshaveh. Okay,
so as opposed to our משנה mishna which just taught that you
split it equally, he teaches a ברייתא braita that says that first
whatever you are physically have in your hand, that's presumed to be
yours. So if one guy actually has
two thirds, has a half of it not just physically in his
hand, he physically
has possession of a half of it, and the other guy is
physically holding on to a quarter of it, then this guy gets
half, this guy gets a quarter, and the middle quarter that's what
you say יחלוקו yachloku to. Okay, that seems very different from our
משנה. mishna.
Now, מחוי ליה רבי אבהו ובשבועה. Machvei lei Rabbi Abbahu uveshvuah.
רש"י Rashi says what it means he signals is he pointed up
to heaven like to God. Okay, yes, it's true you can keep
what's in your hand and so the division won't be down the
middle like the משנה mishna makes it sound, but you still... Still
have to make a שבועה *shvuah*. We, being, we might be sort
of enough to assume that you're in possession and so on, but
we still have this שבועה *shvuah* of כדי שלא יהא כל אחד
ואחד הולך ותוקף טליתו של חבירו ואומר שלי היא *kedei shelo yehei
kol echad ve'echad holech vetokef talliso shel chavero ve'omer sheli hi*. You
know, we're afraid that people are just going to be grabbing somebody
else's טלית tallis, *tallis*. That's not addressed by the fact that one
of them is holding more of it in his hand than the
other. So the שבועה *shvuah* still has to be made. Okay,
fine, but we're still introducing the idea that the division can be
unequal based on how much of it you're holding on to. אלא
מתניתין דקתני דפלגי בהדדי ולא קתני זה נוטל על מקום ידו ומאי
גביה היכי משכחת לה *Ella masnisin de-kateni de-palgi bahadadi velo kateni zeh
notel al makom yado u-megas heichi mashkachat lah*. So the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says, okay, but our משנה *Mishnah* says they split it equally
and it doesn't say you go based on where each person is
holding on to it. How do you explain the משנה *Mishnah* if
you don't want to say the משנה *Mishnah* disagrees? אמר רב פפא
Rav Pappa דתפסי בקרקשתא *Amar Rav Papa detafsi bekarkashta*. They're holding on
to the fringes and the whole טלית talis *tallis* is between them.
They're really not holding on to any part of it that would
lead to an unequal division. You might have remembered before that the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said that holding on to the edge is meaningless,
but that's when somebody else is holding on to the body of
the טלית *tallis* itself. אמר רב משרשיא שמע מינה *Amar Rav Mesharshaya
shma mina*. We can hear from this, this idea that you get
whatever is within your hand, האי סודרא
*hai sudra*, when you use a handkerchief
in
order to do a קנין חליפין *kinyan chalipin*, you know, that somebody
is selling you a car or a piece of land, so the
purchaser gives the seller his handkerchief. The seller takes the handkerchief and
in exchange, the purchaser gets the land or the car or whatever
it is. כיון דתפס ביה שלש על שלש *keivan detafis bei shalosh
al shalosh*, once the seller takes hold of that handkerchief and three
by three—three meaning finger-widths by three finger-widths, okay, so it's like not
even a טפח *tefach* by a טפח *tefach*, it's like you know
whatever it is, about four inches by four inches, something like that—קרינן
ביה ונתן לרעהו *karinan bei venasan lere'ehu*. So that's the שיעור *shiur*
of a בגד *beged*, a minimum size of a garment, and therefore
that would be considered you know that you have given it to
your friend, that he has taken possession of it. Okay, ונתן לרעהו
*venasan lere'ehu*, right, that's by the פסוק *pasuk* in רות *Ruth*, you
know, that זה לפנים בישראל שלף איש נעלו ונתן לרעהו *zeh lepanim
beyisrael shalaf ish na'alo venasan lere'ehu*. So the buyer has already given
his handkerchief to the seller. דכמאן דפסיק דמי *dekeman depasik dami*, what
you're teaching me is that when you're holding onto something, even though
the rest of the garment is out of your hand, it's like
you have fully what you have. You know, we don't look at
the whole garment as a unit; we imagine as if it's cut
off where your hand is and you fully have what you have.
And therefore, he gave you fully an
object. Okay, and
it works. ומאי שנא
מדרב חסדא *u'mai shena mide-Rav Chisda*? Now how is this different from
רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*? דאמר רב חסדא גט בידה ומשיחה בידו *de'amar
Rav Chisda get beyadah u-meshichah beyado*. If a man gives a גט
*get* to his wife and it's in his wife's hand, but he's
holding onto a string that's attached to the גט *get*. אם יכול
לנתקו ולהביאו אצלו אינה מגורשת ואם לאו מגורשת *im yachol lenatko u-lehavi'o
etzlo einah megureshet ve-im lav megureshet*. If he could yank the string
and that will pull the גט *get* out of her hand and
get it to him, then she's not divorced. But if he yanks
it and it's stuck in her hand to the point that he
won't be able to pull it out of her hand, then she
is divorced. So how don't we say it's like it's cut off,
it's all in her hand, who cares that he has the string?
התם כריתות בעינן וליכא הכא נתינה בעינן והאיכא *hatam krisus be'inan velika,
hacha nesinah be'inan vehai'ika*. There it says it has to be a
divider between the husband and the wife. So if he's still holding
onto it, you know, even though conceptually she's still fully in possession
of it, but okay, she's in possession, but he has the ability
to pull it back. The ability to pull it back means that
they're not totally divided. So he might have given it to her,
but they're not yet divided, and that's the problem. Okay, and here
it's just about giving. אמר רבא amar Rava *amar Rava*, says רבא
Rava *Rava*, last of the narrow lines. אם היתה טלית מוזהבת חולקין
im hayesa tallis muzeheves cholkin. *im haytah tallis mu-zehevet cholkin*. Let's say
the טלית *tallis* had gold running down it, you know, it had
golden parts to it woven into it. Then they also divide the
gold equally. פשיטא *pshita*, that's obvious. לא צריכא דהוה במציעתא *lo tzricha
de-hava be-metzi'uta*. So the gold is in the middle, it's not all
equally distributed. היינאמי פשיטא *hai nami pshita*, that's also obvious. לא צריכא
דמקרב לגבי דחד la tzricha dimkarav legabei dechad, *lo tzricha demikrav legabei
de-chad*. No,
let's say the gold is on the first third of the טלית
*tallis*, you know, and so it's closer to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*. ראובן
Reuven *Reuven* is holding one end, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* is holding the
other end, and the gold is closer to the end that ראובן
Reuven *Reuven* is holding. So maybe I would say give it to
ראובן Reuven *Reuven*, you know, you split the טלית *tallis* in the
middle, ראובן Reuven. *Reuven* gets all the gold. מהו דתימא דאמר ליה
פלוג הכי *mahu detaima d'amar leh plog hachi*. ראובן Reuven *Reuven* could
say cut it widthwise now in the middle, give me all the
gold. קמ"ל דאמר ליה מאי חזית דפלגת הכי פלוג הכי *ka mashma
lan d'amar leh mai chazit defalga hachi plog hachi*. What makes you
think you split it this way? Split it that way. What makes
you think that we divide it down widthwise down the middle? Let's
cut it lengthwise and therefore, you know, we get it equally. As
we'll see later you don't actually cut the טלית in half, you
know, you figure out how much it's worth and you divide the
value. But still I might have thought that if the gold is
closer to one of them, maybe that gives him more rights and
it's telling us that that is not true. All right, now we
get to a very fascinating case that we apply this principle of
dividing not only to an object that has intrinsic worth like a
garment, but even a document that its value is just how you
can use it to collect a debt. Let's take a look. תנו
רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught: שניים אוחזים בשטר, shnayim ochazim beshtar,
two people are holding onto a שטר, shtar, a, an IOU document
that says that ראובן Reuven owes שמעון Shimon a thousand dollars. Okay.
מלווה אומר malve omer and ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are both
holding onto it. מלווה אומר, malve omer, the שמעון Shimon who is
the loaner, the creditor says שלי היא ונפלה ממני ומצאתיה sheli hi
venafala mimeni umetzatiha that he says that it's mine, I you know,
I lent ראובן Reuven a thousand dollars and I was carrying around
this IOU and waiting till you know holding onto it until he
would pay it back and then I dropped my, I lost it
and then I refound it and now he's trying to yank it
away from me. ולווה אומר velove omer and now ראובן Reuven the
borrower says no, שלך הייתה shelcha hayita or הוא hu it says
but the other גרסא girsa says הייתה, hayita, it was yours, you
know, I did borrow the thousand dollars ופרעתי לך uvarati lach and
but I paid it up and therefore what happens when you pay
up the debt, you get back your IOU and it fell from
me but the debt's already been paid. So what do you do?
יתקיים השטר בחותמיו דברי רבי. yitkayem hashtar bechotamav divrei rebbi. רבי Rebbi
says you get the witnesses to testify that it's their signature and
then what? Doesn't say, but it sounds like he's saying and then
we would give it to שמעון Shimon and let him collect his
debt which is bizarre. Why? Why should that be the case? We'll
see what the גמרא Gemara says. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר יחלוקו
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer yachloku and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says it's like the case of the טלית, you
don't know who to give it to, they're both in possession, split
it in half. Okay, whether that means split the debt in half
or split the value of a שטר. shtar. The value of a
שטר shtar is not worth a thousand dollars. You know, it's like
when people buy debt from a credit agency. The value might be
worth nine hundred dollars. You don't know in the end if you're
going to be able to collect from ראובן. Reuven Okay, so anyway,
but some version of splitting, either splitting the amount or splitting the
value of the שטר. shtar. יחלוקו. yachloku.
נפל ליד דיין, nafal leyad dayan, if it fell into the hands
of a judge, לא יוציאו לעולם, lo yotziu leolam, then leave it
in their hands, don't do anything with it. Which is bizarre. Why
judge? And how is that different than it's the hands of a
third party? All these things the גמרא Gemara will explain. רבי יוסי
אומר הרי הוא בחזקתו. Rebbi Yossi omer harei hu bechezkatov. We assume
that it's in its default status. What does that mean? Okay, so
now we're going to explain every single one of these. אמר מר.
amar mar. So let's go back and look at each piece by
piece. יתקיים השטר בחותמיו. yitkayem hashtar bechotamav. So according to רבי Rebbi
you validate the signatures. So the גמרא Gemara says וגבי ליה מלווה
כולה? vegovi lei malve kula? And what? Once you validate the signatures
you're going to let שמעון Shimon the creditor collect the whole thing?
ולית ליה למתניתין שניים אוחזים velait lei lematnitin shnayim ochazim whatever? Do
you not hold of our Mishnah two people are holding on you
split it? Why here am I giving more you know am I
basically handing it over to the מלווה? malve? אמר רבא אמר רב
נחמן amar Rav Nachman במקוים דברי הכל יחלוקו. bimkuyam divrei hakol yachloku.
Look.
If the שטר shtar that they're that they're yanking on has already
had the signatures validated, you know, people testified that they were the
right signatures and you got the court's insignia on it, it's like
notarized, then everybody agrees, it's a thousand dollar שטר shtar and they're
each one has a different piece of it, split it down the
middle. כי פליגי בשאינו מקוים. ki peligi besheino mekuyam. The case is
like it sounds like that it has yet to be validated witnesses.
רבי סבר מודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו. Rebbi savar modeh beshtar sheketavo
tzarich lekayemo.
That even though, like here's the thing.
ראובן Reuven, is saying is is the borrower and he's admitting that
the שטר shtar was written but he's saying I paid it up.
Okay. In such a case right if you can't get witnesses to
validate the signature and the so a שטר shtar without validated witnesses
can't be can't be used. But but we know that it's a
good שטר shtar because because the borrower is admitting to it. ראובן
Reuven is admitting to it. So here's the question: do you say
look, ראובן admitted to it, so we know it's a good שטר
shtar and if you have a good שטר shtar the the borrower
is not believed to say he paid it up, right? A שטר
shtar against the claim that he paid it, you believe the מלווה
malve that's holding onto the שטר. shtar. That's one way of looking
at it. Okay. The other way is wait a minute, the only
reason it's a שטר shtar without validated signatures is because of because
the borrower admitted to that, but the same borrower also said that
he paid it up. So it's sort of like הפה שאסר הוא
הפה שהתיר. hapeh sheasar hu hapeh shehitir. If you're going to believe
him partly you should believe him the whole way and therefore actually
you can't collect with that שטר. shtar. So that's the debate of
מודה בשטר שכתבו, modeh beshtar sheketavo, the borrower admits that the שטר
shtar was written against him. It does not have validated signatures.
He's believed to say he paid it up. And if you want,
you the lender, want to collect it, you have to validate the
signatures. Otherwise, it's only a שטר shtar because of him and you
can't use it against him, he says he paid up. So that's
מודה בשטר שכתבו, modeh b'shtar she'ktavo, צריך לקיימו. tzarich l'kaymo. The other
opinion is מודה בשטר שכתבו, modeh b'shtar she'ktavo, אין צריך לקיימו. ein
tzarich l'kaymo.
Fundamentally a שטר shtar even without validated signatures, even if they're not
validated, is kosher מדאורייתא. m'de'oraita. עדים החתומים על השטר כמי שנחקרה עדותם
בבית דין. edim hachatumim al hashtar k'mi shenechkera edutam b'veit din. It's
only the Rabbis that demanded that we validate the signatures. So in
the end of the day, yes, you did away with the need
for validation because the לוה loveh admitted to it. But fundamentally, you
have a שטר, shtar, and therefore he is not believed to say
he paid it off. That's מודה בשטר שכתבו, modeh b'shtar she'ktavo, אין
צריך לקיימו. ein tzarich l'kaymo. Once the לוה loveh admitted to it,
then it's a good שטר shtar and he's not believed to say
פרעתי. parati. Okay, that's the background. Let's see how this fits in.
Okay, כי פליגי, ki pligi, when do they debate? בשאינו מקוים, be'she'eino
mikuyam, that it is not validated. רבי Rebbi סבר, savar, מודה בשטר
שכתבו, modeh b'shtar she'ktavo, צריך לקיימו, tzarich l'kaymo, that even though
ראובן admitted to it, the לוה loveh admitted to it, you can't
collect it against him because he said he paid up. ואי מקיים
ליה, v'ei mkayem leh, so when רבי Rebbi says that you need
to be מקיים, mkayem, what רבי Rebbi is saying is don't not
validate the signatures and give it to the מלוה. malveh. רבי Rebbi
is saying if, only if you validate the signatures, then it's a
good שטר shtar and then we'll say יחלוקו, yachloku, and then we'll
divide it. Okay, אי מקיים ליה פליגי, ei mkayem leh palig, if
you validate, then we would divide, okay. ואי לא מקיים ליה, v'ei
lo mkayem leh, but as long as you haven't validated it, לא
פליגי, lo palig, then you don't divide the שטר. shtar. It's worthless.
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? חספא בעלמא הוא, chaspa b'alma hu, it's like
a piece of pottery. מאן קמשוי ליה להאי שטרא? man kamshavei leh
l'hai shtra? Who turns this into a שטר? shtar? לוה, loveh, the
לוה, loveh, the borrower, by admitting that it was written. הא קאמר
דפריע, ha ka'amar d'paria, he says it's been paid off. So when
רבי Rebbi says you have, they're debating this שטר, shtar, you have
to validate it, he means that it is not a, that the
שטר shtar is worthless until it's validated. Once you get it validated,
then we'll say יחלוקו. yachloku. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר, v'Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel savar, but Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel just says straight יחלוקו,
yachloku,
even without being validated. סבר, savar, מודה בשטר שכתבו, modeh b'shtar she'ktavo,
אין צריך לקיימו. ein tzarich l'kaymo. Once the לוה loveh admitted that
it was written, there's no need to validate
and he is no longer believed to say that it's been paid
up. He's no longer believed, the לוה loveh is not believed to
say פרעתי, parati, even though the לוה loveh was the one who
admitted that it was written against him. And therefore he would say
in this case, since the לוה loveh is saying yes, it was
written against me but I paid it up, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says ha, caught you, you admitted that it
was written, you're not believed to say it was paid up, and
therefore we're going to say, you know, יחלוקו, yachloku, because we view
this as a שטר מקוים. shtar mikuyam. So ואף על גב דלא
מקיים ליה, v'af al gav d'lo mkayem leh, even without being מקיים
mkayem it, יחלוקו. yachloku. So they're really not debating, you know, something
about שנים אוחזין בשטר. shnayim ochzin b'shtar. They're really just debating how
do you deal with a שטר shtar that's not מקוים mikuyam that
the לוה loveh says yes it was written but I paid it
up. Okay, so רבי Rebbi says you gotta be מקיים mkayem it
before it's worth anything, then you would say יחלוקו. yachloku. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says even without being מקיים mkayem
it, since it was admitted to, יחלוקו. yachloku. Okay, now. נפלו ליד
דיין לא יוציאם לעולם. naflu l'yad dayan lo yotzi'am l'olam. If it
fell into the hands of a judge, then you never, you can
never use it, you never give it back to the מלוה. malveh.
So top here of ז עמוד ב. zayin amud bet. מאי שנא
ליד דיין, mai shna l'yad dayan,
why is it different if it fell into the hands of the
judge? What does that mean? A judge finds it, somehow it's different
than if a normal person off the street finds it? אמר רבא
הכי קאמר, amar Rava hachi ka'amar, this is what it means. ואחר
שמצא שטר שנפל ליד דיין, v'acher she'matza shtar she'nafal l'yad dayan,
if a third party, not the מלוה malveh or the לוה, loveh,
some stranger finds a שטר shtar after it had gone through the
hands of a judge, meaning, והיכי דמי, v'heichi dami, what's the case?
דכתב ביה הנפק. d'chtav bei hanpak. You have the, like the court
stamp is on it, okay? It's been, it's been notarized, meaning it's
been a validated שטר. shtar. So if a third party finds a
שטר מקוים, shtar mikuyam, then what do you do? Okay, לא יוציאם
לעולם. lo yotzi'am l'olam.
Then don't ever give it back to the מלוה malveh or the
לוה. loveh. But okay, now why not? ולא מיבעיא לא כתב ביה
הנפק, v'lo mibaya lo chtav bei hanpak, of course if even if
there, it goes without saying that if a third party found an
IOU that ראובן borrowed a thousand dollars from שמעון Shimon. and it
had no, you know, stamp on it, that that would go without
saying that he should never give, never give it to שמעון. Shimon
Why not? ולא מיבעיא לא כתב ביה הנפק דאיכא למימר כתב ללוות
ולא לוה, v'lo mibaya lo chtav bei hanpak d'ika l'meimar chtav lilvot
v'lo lova, that
you could say that, you know, שמעון Shimon, wrote, had this שטר
shtar written out that says, excuse me, ראובן had this שטר shtar
written out that said he borrowed a thousand dollars from שמעון, because
it's his responsibility basically to get the שטר shtar written, and then
he's going to... The loan happened; it might have been written prior
to the loan. So if the witnesses haven't been validated, it hasn't
been gone through the court system, you don't even know if it
was handed over to the creditor. Okay, and then certainly you shouldn't
give it back to the מלווה. malve. אלא אפילו כתוב בה הנפק,
Ella afilu kasuv ba hanpek, even if it's been validated and clearly
it was in the hands of the creditor and it got then
it got validated, even in that case דמקוים demukuyam that it has
been validated, לא יחזיר lo yachzir do not give it back to
the מלווה. malve. Why not? הלווה Halove isn't holding on to it.
It's not a case of שנים אוחזין. shnayim ochzin. You have a
שטר מקוים, shtar mukuyam, so you know that it was in the
hands of the מלווה malve because it had been processed by the
courts. Why don't you give it back to the מלווה? malve? So
why? דחיישינן לפרעון Dechashinan lipiraon because who knows, maybe it did fall
from the hands of ראובן, maybe ראובן paid the debt and he
got the שטר shtar back. All right, so yes it's true it's
not שנים אוחזין, shnayim ochzin, it's a third party, you know it
had been in the hands of the מלווה malve and nevertheless if
they're both holding on to it you split it, they both have
a claim. But here nobody has a claim and therefore don't give
it back to the מלווה, malve, it could have been that it
was already paid up. רבי יוסי אומר הרי הוא בחזקתו Rebbi Yosi
omer harei hu bechezkato and now we understand רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi.
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi is saying no, it's in its default status,
meaning what was the presumed status? We know that it had been
in the hands of the מלווה, malve, that's how it got
the הנפק, hanpek, that's how it got the notarization and therefore we
assume that it fell from the מלווה. malve. We assume
that status
was retained. ולא חיישינן לפרעון V'lo chashinan lipiraon and we're not concerned
that it got paid up. Now one of the reasons we might
not be concerned that it got paid up, it could just be
that we know it had been in the hands of the מלווה
malve and we don't know otherwise. That's the idea of חזקה, chazaka,
but it could also be as רשי Rashi says, because as soon
as you get back that document after you've paid up your debt
you're going to tear it up. So if it isn't torn up,
we're going to assume that it still belongs to the מלווה. malve.
Okay, now the גמרא's Gemara going to question this. ולא חייש רבי
יוסי לפרעון, V'lo chaysh Rebbi Yosi lipiraon, is this really true that
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi is not concerned about that, about a debt
being paid up? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa,
מצא שטר כתובה בשוק, matza shtar kesubah bashuk, somebody found a כתובה
kesubah in the marketplace. בזמן שהבעל מודה, Bizman shehabaal modeh, if the
husband admits
whose possession had it been in? In the wife's.
Now basically the idea here is conceptually the wife is like the
creditor and the husband is the debtor. The husband owes money to
the wife, the wife is holding on like he'll have to pay
when they get divorced or if they get divorced or if he
predeceases her. But the wife has the כתובה, kesubah, has the שטר
shtar against the husband. She's like the creditor, he's like the borrower.
Okay, and now you find this שטר shtar in the marketplace. If
the husband admits that it fell from the wife, יחזיר לאשה yachzir
la'isha give it back to her. אין הבעל מודה Ein habaal modeh
if he says no, I paid it up, then what do you
do? לא יחזיר לא לזה ולא לזה, Lo yachzir lo lizeh velo
lizeh, don't give it back to either. That's similar to what we
just said before, you third party finds it, don't give it back
to either. רבי יוסי אומר Rebbi Yosi omer because you are afraid
that maybe he paid it up. Now of course you're thinking if
they're still married, why might he have paid it up? Okay, we'll
see about that in the גמרא, Gemara but basically the first position
here
is חיישינן לפרעון, chashinan lipiraon, it might have been paid up, don't
give it back to anyone. רבי יוסי אומר עודה תחת בעלה Rebbi
Yosi omer oda tachas baala if she's still married to her husband,
יחזיר לאשה yachzir la'isha then even if he's denying, even if he's
saying he paid it up we don't believe him. We don't assume
that it's been paid while they're still married. You only pay up
a כתובה kesubah after they're divorced. Okay, so if they're still married,
you don't believe him. However, נתארמלה או נתגרשה nisarmela o nisgarsha if
she's widowed or divorced, so then like divorced would be the case
when he's alive and saying he paid it, לא יחזיר לא לזה
ולא לזה lo yachzir lo lizeh velo lizeh then don't give it
back to either. So basically both the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi say we're afraid that it got paid
up and if the husband doesn't agree you don't give it back
to the wife because we are afraid that maybe he paid it
up. The only difference is that רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi doesn't believe
that possibility while they're still married. But fundamentally both positions here are
חיישינן לפרעון. chashinan lipiraon. So why was רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi in
our case of a third party finding a normal שטר shtar not
concerned for פרעון piraon and said you could give it back to
the מלווה? malve? So
the גמרא Gemara says איפוך, ifoch, fine, reverse it. נפול ידידן Nafol
yadidan the first two opinions. לא יחזיר מעולם דברי רבי יוסי, Lo
yechazir me'olam divrei Rebbi Yosi, have רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi be the
one that says that if a third party finds it after it's
been מקוים mukuyam then don't give it back. וחכמים אומרים הרי הוא
בחזקתו Vachachamim omrim harei hu bechezkato
and it's the חכמים Chachamim who say no, we're not concerned for
פרעון piraon give it back. But how have you... improved anything? Because
in this case of the כתובה ketubah both sides held that we
were חיישינן לפירעון. cheyshinan l'piraon. So the גמרא Gemara asks this. So
the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי קשיא דרבנן אדרבנן. Ee hachi kashya
derabbanan a-derabbanan. So fine, we're now back to where we were. You
have the contradiction of the rabbis and the rabbis. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, שטר כתובה כולה רבי יוסי. Shtar ketubah kullah Rabbi
Yossi. We're going to solve that by turning this ברייתא braita about
the כתובה ketubah not into two opinions but all into רבי יוסי's
Rabbi Yossi opinion. וחיסורי מחסרא והכי קתני Vechisurei mechasra vehachi katani because
you can't do away with רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi name, רבי יוסי's
Rabbi Yossi name is in that ברייתא braita about the שטר כתובה.
shtar ketubah. But you can erase the רבנן rabbanan because they were
just an anonymous
present. And here's how you could read it. הכי קתני, Hachi katani,
here's how you read it: אין הבעל מודה, Ein habaal modeh, if
the husband doesn't agree, לא יחזיר לא לזה ולא לזה. lo yachazir
lo la-zeh velo la-zeh. Don't give it back to either because why?
חיישינן לפירעון. cheyshinan l'piraon. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when is
that true? שנתגרשה או שנתאלמנה, shenitgarsha o shenitalmena, once they're divorced or
he died. אבל עודה תחת בעלה, Aval odah tachat baalah, but if
they're still married, יחזיר לאשה, yachazir la-ishah, then you're not concerned of
it being paid up. If they're still married, it's like the time
for it to be paid hasn't arrived yet. Then you don't believe,
then you're not concerned for that. דברי רבי יוסי, Divrei Rabbi Yossi,
that's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi holds. דרבי יוסי אומר De-Rabbi Yossi
omer because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would say עודה תחת בעלה יחזיר
לאשה, odah tachat baalah yachazir la-ishah, while they're still married give it
back to the wife. שנתגרשה או שנתאלמנה, Shenitgarsha o shenitalmena, once they're
divorced, לא יחזיר לא לזה ולא לזה, lo yachazir lo la-zeh velo
la-zeh, don't give it back to either. So the ברייתא braita by
כתובה ketubah makes it clear according to both opinions חיישינן לפירעון. cheyshinan
l'piraon. So what the גמרא Gemara does is it erases the רבנן
rabbanan or it makes it all רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and says
חיישינן לפירעון cheyshinan l'piraon except while they're still married. And then it
reverses the cases about the two people holding onto the שטר shtar
or the שטר shtar being found by a third party and has
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi being the one that's concerned for being paid
up and the רבנן rabbanan not being concerned. That's one answer. רב
פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, רב פפא says לעולם לא תיפוך. Le-olam
lo teipoch.
Don't reverse the first ברייתא braita about the שטר shtar being found
by a third party. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi keep the way it
is. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is not concerned for פירעון. piraon.
He says הרי הוא בחזקתו, harei hu bechezkato, give it back to
the מלווה. malveh. So then why doesn't he always just give it
back to the wife in the case of the כתובה? ketubah? So
רבי יוסי לדרבנן קאמר Rabbi Yossi l'derabbanan ka-amar
because he's really talking to the רבנן rabbanan saying, "According to your
way of thinking." And this is what he's saying: לדידי, Ledidi, as
far as I, רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, am concerned, אפילו שנתגרשה או
שנתאלמנה נמי לא חיישינן לפירעון. afilu shenitgarsha o shenitalmena nami lo cheyshinan
l'piraon. Even if they would be divorced, I'd give it back to
the wife. I say הרי הוא בחזקתו, harei hu bechezkato, that's what
I said over there by the שטר shtar that was found by
a third party. I would always say give it back to the
wife, you assume it's in the hands of the creditor. That's my
opinion. אפילו שנתגרשה או שנתאלמנה נמי לא חיישינן לפירעון. Afilu shenitgarsha o
shenitalmena nami lo cheyshinan l'piraon. אבל לדידכו, Aval l'didchu,
but according to you, the
רבנן, rabbanan, who disagree with me and you're normally concerned about פירעון,
piraon, so לדידכו אודו לי מיהת, l'didchu odu li mihat, at least
you should concede to me בעודה תחת בעלה דיחזיר לאשה be-odah tachat
baalah d'yachazir la-ishah that if they're still married, then you should concede
we're not concerned about it being paid up, then at least you
should give it back to the woman.
And what would they say? ואמרו ליה רבנן, Ve-amru lei rabbanan, the
רבנן rabbanan would say back to it, אימר צררי אתפסה. eimar tzararei
atpasa. No, maybe he bundled up money, meaning even if they're still
married, it could be that he prepaid the כתובה, ketubah, put it
in escrow, and he got the document back from her and that
money she has already been given to her even though they are
still married to one another. That happens sometimes. So answer number two
is that it's what we always thought. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is
not concerned for פירעון. piraon. How about what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
says about the כתובה? ketubah? He was just saying you רבנן rabbanan
that you are concerned for פירעון, piraon, you should admit at least
in a case when they're still married. But as far as I'm
concerned, we always give it back to the woman. That's answer number
two. אמר רב אלעזר, Amar Rav Elazar, says רב אלעזר. Rav Elazar.
I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says לעולם איפוך קמייתא. le-olam eipoch
kamaitha. I'm going to go back, I like the first approach. Reverse
the positions. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is the one
that says חיישינן לפירעון, cheyshinan l'piraon, that we are concerned.
So now what do you do with the חכמים? chachamim? So he
says like
this: וטעמייהו דרבנן הכא משום דחיישינן לשתי כתובות. Vetaamayhu derabbanan hacha mishum
decheyshinan lishtei ketubot.
The רבנן, rabbanan, and this will help explain why they have an
issue even while they're still married. The רבנן rabbanan are not concerned
for פירעון. piraon. Reverse the first teaching we had about the שטר,
shtar, the רבנן rabbanan say הרי הוא בחזקתו, harei hu bechezkato, always
give it back to the מלווה, malveh, they're not concerned for פירעון,
piraon, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is the one that says no,
we're concerned for פירעון, piraon, never give it back to the מלווה.
malveh. Now let's get to the כתובה ketubah case. So we get
how רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is concerned for פירעון. piraon. So we
get how רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, who's concerned for פירעון, piraon, he
says that don't give it back to the husband and wife, I
mean if they're still married fine you can give it to the
wife, but otherwise don't give it back, we're concerned for פירעון. piraon.
How about the חכמים? Chachamim? The חכמים Chachamim are not concerned for
פירעון piraon and they also say don't give it back to the
wife. Why? So now let's find out for a very different reason.
So the גמרא says like this: וטעמא דרבנן
הכא, vetaama deRabbanan hacha, the reason of the Rabbis is משום דחיישינן
לשתי כתובות, mishum dechaishinan lishtei kesuvos,
not because we're concerned of פירעון, piraon, they're not concerned of פירעון.
piraon. Don't give it back to the wife because maybe they got
a second כתובה ksuva written. Okay, and therefore
what happened? They lost this כתובה, ksuva, that's clear, somebody found it,
and maybe he wrote her a replacement כתובה. ksuva. And now they
found this one. So the Rabbis are saying normally we're not concerned
for פירעון, piraon, okay, normally if it was a case about a
normal creditor and a debtor, if my creditor lost the IOU, I
wouldn't have another one written up, I'd say go find it or
else I'm not going to pay you. But in a case of
a husband and wife, so therefore normally the Rabbis would
say we're not concerned for פירעון piraon and give it back to
the מלווה. malve. But in a case of a husband and wife,
if the wife loses it, she says, look,
we can't stay living together without a כתובה ksuva so you get
a replacement written. So that's a likely scenario, and therefore when you
find the כתובה, ksuva, don't give it back to the wife. And
that's why don't give it back even while they're still married. Nothing
to do with we're concerned for פירעון, piraon, we're not concerned for
פירעון, piraon, but in a case of husband and wife don't give
it back because we're concerned for שתי כתובות. shtei kesuvos. Okay, וטעמא
דרבנן הכא משום דחיישינן לשתי כתובות, vetaama deRabbanan hacha mishum dechaishinan lishtei
kesuvos, ורבי יוסי, veRabbi Yosi, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi would say
back, לשתי כתובות לא חיישינן, lishtei kesuvos la chaishinan, I'm not concerned
for two כתובות. ksuvos. So therefore I say that if they're still
married you always give it back to the wife, but if they're
not married I am concerned for פירעון. piraon. Okay, so an interesting
way of making the debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and the
חכמים Chachamim a little more interesting, right? That the Rabbis have a
reason to be willing to give it back while they're married, they're
concerned for שתי כתובות, shtei kesuvos, רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi concern is
elsewhere. Okay, אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, says רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, מחלוקת, machlokes, the now normally מחלוקת ב-X machlokes be-X sounds like
they're debating only this case and this case they agree, but רש״י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both say that this won't make sense in
and here and what this really means is the idea that we
do an equal division, okay, like חלוקה, chaluka, בששניהם אדוקין בטופס ובשניהם
בתורף. besheshneihem adukin batofes ubeshneihem batoref. When would we do an equal
division of this שטר shtar when the מלווה malve and לוה love
are holding on, when they're equally holding on to the טופס tofes
and the תורף. toref. Now the תורף toref is the part that
has the juicy details in it. Who's the מלווה, malve, who's the
לוה, love, how much money, what's the time, what's the date? Okay,
the טופס tofes is more the boilerplate. So if they're equally holding
on, this one is the טופס tofes and this is the טופס,
tofes, this is the תורף, toref, this is the תורף, toref, it's
all equal, then you divide it equally.
Okay, אבל אחד אדוק בטופס ואחד אדוק בתורף, aval echad aduk batofes
ve-echad aduk batoref, if one is holding onto the boilerplate and the
other is holding onto the one with the specific
details, זה נוטל טופס וזה נוטל תורף. zeh notel tofes vezeh notel
toref. This one gets the boilerplate and this one gets the details.
Now what does that mean? Like
a
שטר shtar without both parts even in either the boilerplate to be
כשר kosher and without the whole שטר shtar it's not valuable, so
anyway so we'll see, okay? רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, לעולם
חולקין ואפילו אחד אדוק בטופס ואחד אדוק בתורף. leolam cholkin va-afilu echad
aduk batofes ve-echad aduk batoref. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, you
know what, even in that case you divide it equally, okay, you
divide even if one is the טופס tofes and one is the
תורף. toref. So now the גמרא says, we'll see in a minute
what this division means about טופס tofes and תורף. toref. I mean,
how would you divide it unequally?
Okay, הא תניא זה נוטל עד מקום שידו מגעת. ha tanya zeh
notel ad mekom sheyado magaat. But one minute, how could רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan say that you divide it equally, don't we have this
principle: you get what you're holding
onto? לא צריכא דקאי תורף בי מציעא. la tzricha dekai toref bei
metzia. It means that if the תורף toref is in the middle,
then in that case you get the unimportant part that you're holding
and the other guy gets the unimportant part he's holding. So the
גמרא says, אי הכי מאי למימרא, ei hachi mai lemeimra, so what's
the telling you, like who cares that you get the unimportant part?
לא צריכא דמקרב לגבי דחד, similar to the case of the golden
טלית, the תורף, toref, the essence of it, is closer to one
person's side of the
שטר. shtar. מהו דתימא ניפלוג הכי, mahu deteima niflog hachi, split it
widthwise and therefore I'll take the תורף, toref, קמשמע לן דאמר ליה
מאי חזית דפלגת הכי פלוג הכי. kamashma lan deamar leih mai chazeis
defalgas hachi pelog hachi. What makes you think cut it widthwise, cut
it lengthwise. All right, anyway, all of that we still don't really
know what we're talking about. What does this mean, to get the
תורף toref and to get the טופס? tofes? Clearly the תורף toref
is the more desirable part of the שטר, shtar, but how could
what. What would that mean? So let's take a look. אמר ליה
רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא. Amar leh Rav Acha mi-Difti l'Ravina. So Rav
Acha mi-Difti said to Ravina. ורב אלעזר דאמר זה נוטל טופס וזה
נוטל תורף. v'Rav Elazar d'amar zeh notel Tofes v'zeh notel Toref. According
to this idea that we distinguish between the טופס Tofes and the
תורף, Toref, למה
ליה? Lama leh? So what good is it going to have you
to get one or to get the other? וכי לצור פי צלוחיתו
הוא צריך? V'chi l'tzor pi tzlochito hu tzarich? Do you need it
to bind up against your bottle? What, you want the piece of
paper to use as a bottle stopper? That's not what you care
about, you care about the value of the שטר. shtar. So what
does it mean to talk about who has the תורף Toref and
who has the טופס, Tofes, you know, which piece of which part
of the paper you have? What does that matter? So אמר ליה,
לדמי. lidmei. No, what it is different, we're going to conceptualize the
value of it differently based on the טופס Tofes and the תורף.
Toref. What does this mean? דאמר הכי, D'amar hachi, this is cause
this is what he says to him: שטר דאית ביה זמן כמה
שוי ודלית ביה זמן כמה שוי. Shtar d'is beh zman kama shavi
u'd'leis beh zman kama shavi. A שטר shtar that has in it
the date, how much is it worth, and that doesn't have the
date, how much is it worth? Okay, so what's the difference?
בשטרא דאית ביה זמן, B'shtara d'is beh zman, if it's got the
date in it, גבי ממשעבדי. gabi mi-mshabdei. Then a שטר shtar with
a date creates liens cause you know when the loan took place
and in order for there to be liens, the people who buy
the land afterwards have to know if there's a lien so you
need a date in it. So if there's a date, then it
has created liens and therefore a thousand dollar שטר shtar with liens
on the property where, you know, it's like a mortgage is worth
a lot more than a thousand dollar שטר shtar with no liens.
Okay. ואידך
לא גבי ממשעבדי v'idach lo gabi mi-mshabdei and without the date, you
can't use it to collect, there are no liens. So let's say
a thousand dollar שטר shtar with liens is worth nine hundred and
fifty dollars and a thousand dollar שטר shtar without liens is worth
seven hundred dollars. Okay.
So ואידך לא גבי ממשעבדי יהיב ליה האי דביני ביני. v'idach lo
gabi mi-mshabdei yaiv leh hai d'beini beini. So if one person has
the תורף, Toref, now I'll get back to in a minute why
the תורף Toref makes the difference here. But if one person has
the תורף, Toref, that's like having the half of the שטר shtar
that's the שטר shtar with the liens. So it's like having, you
know, the sort of the nine hundred dollar שטר, shtar, okay? And
the guy that has the טופס Tofes is like he has half
of the seven hundred dollar שטר shtar because he has the שטר
shtar that without the liens. Okay, so יהיב ליה האי דביני ביני.
yaiv leh hai d'beini beini. So the guy with the תורף Toref
basically cause he's got the nine hundred dollar or nine hundred and
fifty dollar שטר shtar in his possession and you give him the
difference between nine fifty and seven hundred, two fifty. So the תורף
Toref part is worth two fifty. The date adds another which adds
the liens adds a two hundred and fifty dollar value to the
שטר. shtar. So the guy who's holding the תורף, Toref, the מלוה
Malveh or the לוה Loveh gets two hundred and fifty dollars of
the value of the שטר. shtar. The remaining seven hundred you divide
equally. So one of them is going to get, you know, what's
three fifty and two fifty? One of them is going to get
six hundred and one of them is going to get three fifty,
okay, based on who's holding the תורף Toref because the תורף Toref
represents the liens and that's that gives one side that extra value
in the שטר. shtar. והאי דביני ביני ויחלוקו. v'hai d'beini beini v'yachloku.
Okay, ויחלוקו, v'yachloku, so you divide it.
Now,
why does the תורף Toref mean the date? So Rashi has an
explanation which I'm not going to go into. Tosfos basically says because
every part of the שטר shtar is like, you know, repeated. That
that idea of repeated is Rashi's point. Tosfos says like this:
if the שטר shtar is missing any part of it, תורף, Toref,
טופס, Tofes, any part, it would be invalid. The only thing that
a שטר shtar could be missing that wouldn't invalidate it would be
the date. Without the date the שטר shtar is still valid, but
it doesn't have the liens. So therefore Tosfos says if you're holding,
if Reuven's holding part and Shimon's holding part, if we were to
literally cut the שטר shtar and give them the piece they were
holding, either one would invalidate. So since either piece that they're holding
has the power to invalidate, it's like, you know, they're equal. But
if one of them is holding the part that has the date,
that's unequal cause the date is a piece that could be conceptually
separate from the שטר. shtar. It gives added value but it doesn't
it's not necessary for the legitimacy of the שטר. shtar. So the
person holding the date is like they're holding that added value. All
right, it's a funny idea, but anyway that's what the גמרא says.
Okay. Now, ויחלוקו נמי דאמרינן לדמי. V'yachloku nami d'amrinan lidmei.
And when we're talking about dividing it we don't mean literally cut
divided in half with a scissor, we mean you figure out the
value and you divide it according to this formula that we just
said. אי לא תימא הכי, Ei lo teima hachi, if you don't
say that, שנים אוחזין בטלית הכי נמי דפלגי? shnayim ochzin b'talis hachi
nami d'palgi? So do you think division is literal? If they're holding
onto a טלית will you take it your scissor and you cut
it in half? הפסדא הוא? Hafsada hu? Then
you're destroying its value. So the גמרא says no, הא לא קשיא,
ha lo kashya, that by itself wouldn't be difficult. Top of ח
דף עמוד א. ches daf amud aleph. דחזי לקטני. D'chazi l'ktanei. Maybe
you wouldn't destroy its value. Maybe you could have two half טליתות
talisos and each one would be totally good for a minor, for
minors. minors. והדר אמר רבא, ve'hadar amar Rava, one minute, but רבא
says אם היתה טלית מוזהבת חולקין.
If it had gold, you would divide it. הכא נמי דפלגי לה?
hacha nami de'palgig leh? What, you're going to have two little half
טליתות, tallises, טליתות tallises for minors with gold? What, minors wear gold
laces? הפסדא, hefseda, you're destroying the value? No, הא לא קשיא, ha
lo kashya, no, not necessarily, that's not a problem. דחזי לבני מלכים,
de'khazi livnei melachim, maybe you have princes, wealthy kids, who would wear
golden טליתות. tallises. So maybe it does mean you literally cut it
in half. So the גמרא says והתנן, ve'hasnan, היו שנים רוכבים על
גבי בהמה, hayu shnayim rokhvim al gabei behema,
how about a case about riding on an animal? It says you
divide it? הכא נמי דפלגי לה? hacha nami de'palgig leh? What, you're
going to literally cut the animal in half? הפסדא, hefseda, that you're
just, you're just going to waste it. בשלמא בטהורה, bishlama betehora, if
it's a kosher animal, חזיא לבשרא, chazya lebasra, fine, maybe you שחט
shecht it and divide the meat. אלא בטמאה, ela bet'me'ah, but let's
say it's a donkey, הפסדא, hefseda, a dead donkey is worth nothing
to you. אלא לדמי, ela lidmei, obviously all this thing about dividing
means you sell it, you figure out the value, divide the value.
הכא נמי לדמי, hacha nami lidmei, and the same is true about
a שטר. shtar. Okay, so that's the end of our discussion of
the splitting and of the שטר shtar and this very interesting idea
of תופס tofes and תורף. toref.